<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://yamenajjour.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://yamenajjour.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-02-04T12:07:59+00:00</updated><id>https://yamenajjour.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Yamen Ajjour, Research Scientist and PhD in Natural Language Processing [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Position Paper: Problem Solving Through Human-AI Preference-based Cooperation</title><link href="https://yamenajjour.github.io/preference-based%20cooperation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Position Paper: Problem Solving Through Human-AI Preference-based Cooperation"/><published>2025-12-14T10:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-14T10:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yamenajjour.github.io/preference-based-ai-collaboration</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yamenajjour.github.io/preference-based%20cooperation/"><![CDATA[<p>This <a href="https://direct.mit.edu/coli/article-pdf/doi/10.1162/coli.a.19/2539252/coli.a.19.pdf">paper</a> addresses a fundamental problem with today’s Artificial Intelligence: current AI tools are poor teammates.</p> <p>When we ask an AI (like one that writes software or designs a product) to make changes, it struggles to understand and act on our requests, especially when those requests involve big-picture ideas or complex, step-by-step refinements.</p> <p>The Solution: A New Framework for Collaborative AI</p> <p>The researchers propose a new approach to build AI agents that don’t just follow simple instructions, but can genuinely partner with humans to create complex solutions, such as new software programs.</p> <p>The core idea is to treat the process of creation like a shared exploration guided by human feedback (language-based requests or confirmations). The framework is built on several key design choices:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Shared Exploration</strong> (The “Search”): Instead of just giving one answer, the AI should explore a whole range of potential solutions. Human feedback (given in natural language) acts like a compass, helping the AI navigate this space of possibilities toward the best outcome. <ul> <li>Representation: Solutions (like a piece of software) must be understood and talked about at different levels, from the high-level Goals (requirements) to the blueprint (architecture), the design (how parts fit together), and the actual Code (implementation).</li> <li>Quality Check (Utility): The system needs a way to measure the “goodness” of any solution using multiple metrics. For example, is the new computer program fast, or does it use too much memory?</li> <li>Action Steps (Operators): The AI needs a library of actions it can use to modify an existing solution to make it better.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Pre-defined Collaboration (Communication Protocol)</strong>: A defined set of conversational acts is needed to clarify the interaction between the human and the AI. This includes clear ways for the human to Critique a solution, offer Confirmation, or request a specific Modification. Major Unanswered Questions for Research</li> </ol> <p>The framework opens up challenging questions for future research:</p> <ul> <li><em>Learning from Fixes (Edits-based learning)</em>: Instead of saving every piece of conversational context, how can the AI learn general rules by comparing the quality of the solution before a human edit to the quality after the edit?</li> <li><em>Safety in Shared Creation</em>: Since the AI is involved in shaping the final objective, how do we ensure the AI cannot subtly manipulate the goals in a way that is harmful or unsafe?</li> <li><em>Evaluating Teamwork</em>: How do we accurately measure and evaluate the quality and effectiveness of the human-AI collaboration process itself, rather than just the final product?</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Agentic"/><category term="AI"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This paper addresses a fundamental problem with today’s Artificial Intelligence: current AI tools are poor teammates.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Vision Paper: The Agentic State</title><link href="https://yamenajjour.github.io/agentic-state/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vision Paper: The Agentic State"/><published>2025-10-31T09:48:48+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-31T09:48:48+00:00</updated><id>https://yamenajjour.github.io/agentic-government</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yamenajjour.github.io/agentic-state/"><![CDATA[<p>The following is a summary of <a href="https://agenticstate.org/paper.html#whitepaper-reader">the agetnic state</a> which is published at the 2025 Tallinn Digital Summit about the <em>Agentic State</em>. Prominent politicians from around the globe have gathered to come up with a feasible vision that goes beyond a digital government to an Agentic Government. <br/> The main message of the paper is the urgent need for governments to adapt agentic AI in their workflows and provide use cases and the requirements for deploying Agentic AI in a fruitful way. The main reason is the gap confronted by citizens between the internet culture (e.g., Netflix) and the bureaucratic processes enforced by existing governments. The transformation to an AI-based government should be accomplished by realizing twelve layers. The twelve layers are divided into:</p> <ul> <li>Six implementation layers that represent different sectors: <ul> <li>User Interface transform from fragmented portals into centralized, personalized, and multimodal agents.</li> <li>Workflows transform from hand-crafted compliance-first processes to workflows that are dynamically generated by AI-agents to meet a predefined outcome (e.g., A permit agent might be tasked with approving 90% of construction applications within ten days while rigorously enforcing zoning and climate standards)</li> <li>Policy and law making transform from being deliberative and static to adaptive and simulation-based. Current governments create laws for old concerns, since it takes years to debate and enact them. An agentic government encodes law as executable logic, which is simulated on digital twins and synthetic populations. The outcome of the law or policy is continuously monitored in terms of success metrics and compliance rates.</li> <li>Regulatory compliance transforms from being periodic and retrospective to being embedded as agents in the two sides of the compliance process: companies and regulators. Current regulator compliance is retrospective in the sense that it happens abruptly and usually addresses rule violations years after they happen (e.g., checking tax evasion years after it happens). Agents at firms can monitor in real-time input, for example, emissions, and report to regulators in real time.</li> <li>Crisis response from being hierarchical to being predictive and simulation-based</li> <li>Public procurement, from being bureaucratic and hence not competitive and fostering small businesses, to being completely automated. AI agents look up suppliers in real time, compare offers, and adapt contracts dynamically to shifting needs. To achieve these use cases, the following layers are needed.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Six enablement layers <ul> <li>Agent Governance: enabling higher accountability, safety, and redress by ethical, legal, and appeal frameworks realized by the agents. The ethical frameworks provide standards and algorithms that promote fairness and transparency. The legal framework links agentic actions to authorized human officials. The appeal framework allows citizens to have control over agents that control their lives.</li> <li>Data and Privacy: treating data as a critical infrastructure and data analysis skill as requirements for each employee. Data should be open by default to allow innovation, but still should be protected for privacy.</li> <li>Tech Stack: five layers of multimodal interfaces, application infrastructure through APIs, orchestration and interoperability layer, digital public infrastructure that provides verifiable digital identity, and a compute cluster.</li> <li>Cybersecurity: Protection against malicious usage</li> <li>Public Finance: Outcome-based pricing models and adaptive contractive</li> <li>Leadership: the strategy needed to transform government workforces</li> </ul> </li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Agentic"/><category term="AI"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following is a summary of the agetnic state which is published at the 2025 Tallinn Digital Summit about the Agentic State. Prominent politicians from around the globe have gathered to come up with a feasible vision that goes beyond a digital government to an Agentic Government. The main message of the paper is the urgent need for governments to adapt agentic AI in their workflows and provide use cases and the requirements for deploying Agentic AI in a fruitful way. The main reason is the gap confronted by citizens between the internet culture (e.g., Netflix) and the bureaucratic processes enforced by existing governments. The transformation to an AI-based government should be accomplished by realizing twelve layers. The twelve layers are divided into: Six implementation layers that represent different sectors: User Interface transform from fragmented portals into centralized, personalized, and multimodal agents. Workflows transform from hand-crafted compliance-first processes to workflows that are dynamically generated by AI-agents to meet a predefined outcome (e.g., A permit agent might be tasked with approving 90% of construction applications within ten days while rigorously enforcing zoning and climate standards) Policy and law making transform from being deliberative and static to adaptive and simulation-based. Current governments create laws for old concerns, since it takes years to debate and enact them. An agentic government encodes law as executable logic, which is simulated on digital twins and synthetic populations. The outcome of the law or policy is continuously monitored in terms of success metrics and compliance rates. Regulatory compliance transforms from being periodic and retrospective to being embedded as agents in the two sides of the compliance process: companies and regulators. Current regulator compliance is retrospective in the sense that it happens abruptly and usually addresses rule violations years after they happen (e.g., checking tax evasion years after it happens). Agents at firms can monitor in real-time input, for example, emissions, and report to regulators in real time. Crisis response from being hierarchical to being predictive and simulation-based Public procurement, from being bureaucratic and hence not competitive and fostering small businesses, to being completely automated. AI agents look up suppliers in real time, compare offers, and adapt contracts dynamically to shifting needs. To achieve these use cases, the following layers are needed. Six enablement layers Agent Governance: enabling higher accountability, safety, and redress by ethical, legal, and appeal frameworks realized by the agents. The ethical frameworks provide standards and algorithms that promote fairness and transparency. The legal framework links agentic actions to authorized human officials. The appeal framework allows citizens to have control over agents that control their lives. Data and Privacy: treating data as a critical infrastructure and data analysis skill as requirements for each employee. Data should be open by default to allow innovation, but still should be protected for privacy. Tech Stack: five layers of multimodal interfaces, application infrastructure through APIs, orchestration and interoperability layer, digital public infrastructure that provides verifiable digital identity, and a compute cluster. Cybersecurity: Protection against malicious usage Public Finance: Outcome-based pricing models and adaptive contractive Leadership: the strategy needed to transform government workforces]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Book: Learning to learn</title><link href="https://yamenajjour.github.io/learning-to-learn/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book: Learning to learn"/><published>2024-11-01T09:48:48+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-01T09:48:48+00:00</updated><id>https://yamenajjour.github.io/learning-to-learn</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yamenajjour.github.io/learning-to-learn/"><![CDATA[<p>While doing some research on Meta Learning, I came across the book of <a href="https://radekosmulski.com/">Radek Osmulski</a>. The book is titled META LEARNING and basically reports valuable information on how to become a deep learning scientist. It gives really personal advice to all those who want to become to use deep learning to have an impact on this field.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/meta-learning-book.png" alt="META Learning Book"/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="deep-learning"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[While doing some research on Meta Learning, I came across the book of Radek Osmulski. The book is titled META LEARNING and basically reports valuable information on how to become a deep learning scientist. It gives really personal advice to all those who want to become to use deep learning to have an impact on this field.]]></summary></entry></feed>